哈喽大家好我是凯超
Hello everyone, I am Kaichao
本次课程的内容是
Today's course is to develop a module for Proof of Existence using Substrate
使用substrate开发一个
存证功能的模块
Today's course is to develop a module for Proof of Existence using Substrate
本次课程的内容包括
The content of this course includes
存证的一个简单介绍
a brief introduction to Proof of Existence
接着我们会一起动手写代码
then we'll write the code together
最后我们会看一下我们这节课的作业
finally we'll look at our homework for this lesson
那么什么是链上存证呢
So what is onchain Proof of Existence (PoE)?
存证本质上是一种在线服务
Proof of existence is essentially an online service that can be implemented using traditional web technology or blockchain technology
既可以使用传统的互联网技术
也可以使用区块链技术
Proof of existence is essentially an online service that can be implemented using traditional web technology or blockchain technology
它用于在某个时间点记录计算机文件
It is used to record a computer file at a certain point in time and verify the existence of the file
并且验证计算机文件的存在性
链上存证最早是通过在比特币网络
Onchain proof of existence was initially achieved by creating a transaction with a timestamp on the Bitcoin network
生成一个带有时间戳的交易
来进行实现
Onchain proof of existence was initially achieved by creating a transaction with a timestamp on the Bitcoin network
存证典型的应用场景有数字版权
Typical application scenarios for Proof of Existence includes
可以把创作者创作的内容音乐
digital copyright can establish ownership and protect the rights of creators by recording their creative content such as music or videos on the blockchain
视频等上链来进行版权的确权
司法存证
judicial proof stores the process, outcome of litigation, and the accompanying evidence on the blockchain for preservation
将判决的结果判决的过程
以及判决的证据
judicial proof stores the process, outcome of litigation, and the accompanying evidence on the blockchain for preservation
通过上链来进行保存
从而在有需要的情况下可以进行追溯
this enables easy traceability and verification when needed
另外一个是供应链溯源
another one is supply chain traceability
在现实世界中
in the real world, ensuring the quality of food and vegetables can be challenging
我们经常吃的食物和蔬菜
很多时候它的质量难以保证
in the real world, ensuring the quality of food and vegetables can be challenging
通过将对应的供应链信息进行上链
by recording corresponding supply chain information on the blockchain, it helps improve food quality
能够更好的进行质量的保护
还可以用于电子发票的上传
It can also be used to upload electronic invoices
可以杜绝某些不良企业虚开发票等等
which can prevent fraudulent activities, such as issuing fake invoices from dishonest companies
我们现在就来看一下如何使用substrate
Let's take a look at how to use Substrate to implement onchain proof of existence functionality
来实现一个链上存证的功能
本次课程是基于substrate.dev的一个
This course is based on a tutorial about PoE provided by substrate.dev
构建存证这样的一个教程
大家有兴趣的话
If you're interested, you can follow the tutorial's instructions step by step to create your own implementation
也可以根据教程的资料一步一步的去做一下
我们需要使用到一个substrate
We need to use a template program substrate-node-template provided by Substrate
提供的模板程序
叫做substrate-node-template
We need to use a template program substrate-node-template provided by Substrate
这里我们使用我们通过get clone命令
Here, we use the git clone command with the -b flag to specify the version we want to clone
这里我们是使用
-b来指定我们的版本号是
Here, we use the git clone command with the -b flag to specify the version we want to clone
depth-1是指我们
--depth 1 means that we only clone the latest commit
克隆最新的一个commit
它的历史记录我们并不会再下载
it won't download all the commit history
来提高我们下载源代码的速度
which improves the speed of downloading the source code
这里我们使用的substrate-node-template是位于
The substrate-node-template we use here is located at the organization github.com/substrate-developer-hub
github的substrate develop hub这样的一个组织下面
我们进行克隆
let's clone it
我们进入到我们的substrate-node-template
and enter into substrate-node-template
可以看到我们这里使用的一些
You can see here some git commit information
git commit信息
接着我们使用VS code来打开我们的
Next, we use VS Code to open our code
代码当然
大家也可以选择适合自己的一个IDE
you can also choose an IDE that suits you
可以看到这就是substrate-note-template的
this is the directory and files of substrate-note-template
目录文件
它有一些Readme的信息
readme file contains some helpful information
帮助性的信息
大家也可以读一下
read it too
我相信大家之前也多少读过
I believe many of you have read the code inside the note template before
note template里面的代码
还可以使用docker来进行启动
You can also use docker to start the dev environment when using windows
当你的本地环境是windows的时候
你可以选择使用docker这样的一种机制
You can also use docker to start the dev environment when using windows
Cargo.toml里面定义了我们
Cargo.toml includes different members for the node template program
node template的一个不同的成员
rust里面可以使用workspace来
In Rust, you can use a workspace to organize a complex project
组织一个复杂的工程项目
那我们的node template里面
In our node template, we have several members
有这样几个member
一个是node的
"node" represents our executable program for the blockchain node
表示我们的节点可执行的程序
pallets表示了我们链上的一些功能模块
"pallets" contains the functional modules on our chain
那runtime的话就是我们
and "runtime" is to assemble onchain logic such as different modules
链上runtime的这样一个集合
现在我们就可以来编写我们对应的
Now we can start writing the proof of existence module
存证相关的模块
我们打开pallets目录
open the pallets directory
它已经有了一个template
it already has a template module
这样的一个功能模块
我们现在新建一个poe这样的一个模块
Now we create a new module called poe
我们新建一个folder poe
first create a new folder named poe
然后我们加入我们的依赖Cargo.toml
then add Cargo.toml
我们直接拷贝
simply copy the Cargo.toml file from the template module and modify the necessary information
template模块的Cargo.toml文件
然后修改我们对应的信息
simply copy the Cargo.toml file from the template module and modify the necessary information
模块名是pallet poe
change the module name to pallet-poe
proof existence
and the description is proof of existence
其他信息我们暂时不去修改
we will not modify other information for now
可以看到我们这里依赖
As you can see, we depend on "codec" for encoding and decoding
codec编辑码这样一个包
以及scale-info可以帮助我们把
"scale-info" helps us with encoding and decoding the types of onchain storage items
链上存储项的类型进行编解码
以及自动的导出给前端使用
and automatically exports them for frontend use
frame-support依赖添加了
frame-support adds some macros and traits required for runtime development
runtime开发所需要的一些宏和接口
frame-system定义了系统接口
frame-system defines the system config trait which includes some common data types such as BlockNumber and Hash
包含了一些常用的数据类型比如区块数BlockNumber以及哈希这样的数据类型
frame-benchmarking可以用来方便的去进行基准测试
frame-benchmarking can be used to facilitate benchmarking
我们会在后面的课程中进行介绍
we'll cover that later in the course
以及用于测试的dev dependencies
There are also dev dependencies for testing
接着我们添加我们的模块代码
Next let's add our module's code
我们需要先创建一个folder是src
we need to create a new folder called "src" and place the lib.rs file inside the src folder
然后把lib.rs原文件放在src目录下面
这里因为我们新的版本跟之前
Here the code may be slightly different with previous versions because of the version updates
入门课的版本可能有比较大出入
所以我们
let's go through the source code of the proof of existence module together
这里带大家一起来敲一下
存证模块的源代码
let's go through the source code of the proof of existence module together
同样的我们要添加编译标签
Here we need to add the feature for conditional compilation
如果不是使用std feature编译的话那么就使用no_std属性
it means if the build is not using the std feature then use the no_std attribute
接着我们使用pub use这样的方式来
Then, we use the "pub use" syntax to export the content defined in the poe module
导出poe模块定义的内容
比如存储单元给外部来使用
such as storage items for external use
接着我们来定义我们的Poe模块
Next, let's define our PoE module and place it within a module namespace called pallet
我们把它放在一个模块空间pallet里
我们需要添加所需要的
We need to add frame_support::pallet macro
frame_support::pallet这样的一个宏
我们把字体进行放大
let's increse the font size for better view
现在应该会看得比较清楚
我们引入frame_support的依赖
Import the dependencies from frame_support using the path frame_support::pallet_prelude::*
使用frame_support::pallet_prelude::*这样的路径来引入
预定义的一些依赖
Import the dependencies from frame_support using the path frame_support::pallet_prelude::*
比如我们刚才提到的frame_support
such as some common traits like Get, and macros
提供的一些通用接口比如Get接口
以及一些常用的宏
such as some common traits like Get, and macros
同样我们引入frame_system这样的依赖
Similarly, we introduce dependencies from frame_system
它的prelude里面包含了ensure_signed, ensure_none
in its prelude, there are helper functions like ensure_signed, ensure_none
这样的一个方便地进行签名验证的方法
which are convenient for transaction verification
引入依赖之后
After importing the dependencies, now we can define the module's config trait
我们就可以去定义我们的模块配置接口
我们是使用rust里面的trait来定义的
it's defined with Rust trait syntax
trait config
the trait is named Config
我们的模块接口叫做Config
然后它继承自frame system的Config接口
it inherits from the Config trait of the frame_system module
这样的话
by doing this
我们的config接口里面就拥有了system config接口里面定义的一些数据类型
our Config trait inherits the data types defined in the frame_system module's Config trait
比如我们刚提到的BlockNumber表示区块数量
such as BlockNumber, Hash, AccountId types we just mentioned
以及hash这样的一些hash类型
还有AccountId用来表示用户的ID
such as BlockNumber, Hash, AccountId types we just mentioned
也是定义在系统模块内的config接口里
同样的我们不要忘记添加所需要的宏
Let's not forget to add the necessary macros
这里用到的是pallet::config的宏
here we use the pallet::config macro
接着
Then, we add some associated types to the module's Config trait
我们添加我们需要的一些关联类型
到模块的config接口里面
Then, we add some associated types to the module's Config trait
这里我们需要用到一个MaxClaimLength
One of the associated types is MaxClaimLength
它是我们存证最大所接受长度限制
which represents the maximum accepted length for a claim in our PoE module
也就是说你的存证不能超过一定的长度
in other words, it limits the length of a claim
如果太长会导致链上的状态爆炸
as having excessively long claim could cause an explosion of onchain state
通常情况下
In general, we only store the hash of the original content
我们在链上只存储原始内容的哈希值
而哈希值的长度是固定的
the length of the hash value is fixed
这里可以看到
Here, you can see that we use a u32 integer type associated with the Get trait
我们使用的是一个Get
接口对应的u32整数类型
Here, you can see that we use a u32 integer type associated with the Get trait
这个类型后续会在我们的存储项BoundedVec
this type will be used later in the BoundedVec of our storage item
这样一个长度受限的集合类型中进行使用
which is a collection type with a limited length
注意这里我们需要使用u32类型
Note that here we need to use the u32 type because BoundedVec only accept such a type for now
因为BoundedVector目前的
长度限制是接受u32这样的数据类型
Note that here we need to use the u32 type because BoundedVec only accept such a type for now
因为它是一个常量
Since it is a constant, we need to use the pallet::constant macro to declare it as a constant type
所以我们需要使用到pallet::constant这个宏
来声明这样的类型是链上的常量
Since it is a constant, we need to use the pallet::constant macro to declare it as a constant type
我们还可以添加一些有意义的注释比如这里的
We can also add some meaningful comments such as
maximum length of claim that can be added
这样的内容可以在前端进行显示
such content can be displayed on the frontend
在配置接口里面
In the config trait, we need another associated type called RuntimeEvent
我们还需要一个通用的
关联类型是叫做Event
In the config trait, we need another associated type called RuntimeEvent
在runtime进行配置接口实现的时候
when implementing the Config trait in the runtime, it will be set to the RuntimeEvent defined in the runtime
会把runtime定义的Event
设置在这样的一个类型里
when implementing the Config trait in the runtime, it will be set to the RuntimeEvent defined in the runtime
我们所要求的event满足这些条件
The event required should meet following conditions
它可以从当前模块
it can be converted from the current module's Event type
Event类型转换过去
同时它是系统模块的event类型
and it is the event type of the system module
定义完配置接口之后
After defining the configuration interface
我们就可以去
we can
定义我们的
define
模块所需要的结构体
the structure required by the module
pallet这样一个结构体
called Pallet
这里我们需要使用
Here we need to use
pallet宏
pallet::pallet macro
因为我们的模块会定义
Because our module will define
自己所需要的存储项
storage items we need
所以我们需要另外一个
So we need another
generate_store这样的宏来帮助我们
generate_store to help us
生成包含所有存储项的
generate
trait Store这样的一个接口
an interface like trait Store
接着
Then
我们就可以定义我们所使用的存储项
we can then define the storage items we use
Proofs
它是一个StorageMap类型
It is a StorageMap type
在Substrate里面
Inside Substrate
我们用StorageMap表示一个键值对
We use StorageMap to represent a key-value pair
这里我们的键是BoundedVector u8
Here our key is BoundedVector u8
也就是u8的一个长度受限的集合
That is, a length-restricted set of u8
在新的版本里面
in the new version
Runtime
runtime
不能直接使用vector集的集合类型
cannot use the collection type of the vector set directly
而是使用BoundedVector
Instead use BoundedVector
这样一个更安全的
such a safer
长度受限的集合类型
length-restricted collection type
它有两个范型参数
It takes two generic parameters
第一个是集合内的元素类型
The first is the element type within the collection
这里我们是U8
Here it is u8
以及第二个范型参数
and the second generic parameter
是BoundedVector所接受的最大长度
is the maximum length accepted by BoundedVector
这里我们是使用我们的关联类型
Here we are using our associated type
MaxClaimLength
来去指定
to specify
注意这里只能接受
Note that it only accepts
get u32这样的一个类型
a type like get u32
StorageMap
的value是一个包含两个元素的Tuple
The value is a Tuple containing two elements
第一个元素是AccountId
The first element is AccountId
第二个元素是BlockNumber
The second element is BlockNumber
表示我们的存证是属于哪个用户
It indicates which user PoE belongs to
是在哪一个区块存储
Which block is stored in
进入我们的链上的
on chain
这里Blake2_128Concat
Here Blake2_128Concat
这样是一个哈希算法
This is a hash algorithm
用来将我们的存储项存储到
which is used to when we store our storage items in
底层数据库的时候
in the underlying database
对它的存储的位置进行哈希计算
to perform a hash calculation on its stored location
我们之前在课程中提到过
We mentioned earlier in the course
Blake2_128Concat是一个密码安全的哈希算法
Blake2_128Concat is a cryptographically secure hash algorithm
还有一些更快速的哈希算法
There are also some faster hashing algorithms
比如TwoX hash
Such as TwoX hash
它们的区别大家可以参考文档
You can refer to the documentation for their differences
或者参考之前的课程
or refer to previous courses
定义完存储之后
After defining storage
我们就可以定义我们所需要的事件
We can define the events we need
可以在交易执行的过程中进行触发
They can be triggered during transaction execution
我们使用generate_deposit这样一个宏
We use a macro like generate_deposit
生成一个帮助方法
to generate a helper method
deposit_event可以方便来调用
deposit_event can be conveniently called
生成事件这样的一个方式
A way to generate events like this
这里我们定义了两个event一个
Here we define two events. One
是ClaimCreated
Is ClaimCreated
包含了AccountId信息和我们claim
which contains AccountId information and our claim
vector u8这样的信息
informations such as vector u8
以及ClaimRevoked
and ClaimRevoked
同样的包含了AccountId和vector u8信息
The same it contains AccountId and vector u8 information
一个事件是在claim创建的时候触发的
An event is triggered when the claim is created
一个事件是在claim吊销之后触发的
An event is triggered after a claim is revoked
接着我们来定义我们的错误信息
Next we define our error messages
我们使用pallet::error
We use pallet::error
这样的宏来定义不同的错误类型
macros like this to define different error types
这里我们定义了几种错误一个是
Here we define several kinds of errors. One is
ProofAlreadyExist
另外一个是ClaimTooLong
The other one is ClaimTooLong
还有ClaimNotExist以及NotClaimOwner
ClaimNotExist and NotClaimOwner
这样的错误我们会在后面的
These errors
可调用函数里面进行使用
can be used inside a callable function later
这里我们提前进行声明
Here we declare in advance
当然大家在开发的时候其实是在
Of course, when you are developing,
编写可调用函数的时候
When writing a callable function
发现了有哪些新的错误类型
What new types of errors were discovered
然后添加到Error这样的一个enum里面
Then add it to an enum like Error
这里我们使用了pallet::hooks这样一个宏
Here we use a macro such as pallet::hooks
来定义一些保留的函数
to define some reserved functions
因为我们
because
存证模块并没有使用任何保留函数
PoE module does not use any reserved functions
所以我们这里把它置空
So we leave it blank here
那些保留的函数通常包括on_initialize
Those reserved functions usually include on_initialize
on_finalize on_time_upgrade等等
on_finalize on_time_upgrade etc.
在区块的不同时机进行执行
They are executed at different times in the block
现在我们就来定义我们的可调函数
Now let's define our callable functions
我们是在
In
pallet结构体的实现里面添加了
the implementation of the pallet structure, we has added
pallet::call这样一个宏
pallet::call such a macro
来去定义我们的可调函数
to define our callable functions
这里我们定义了我们第一个可调函数
Here we define our first callable function
是create_claim
That is create_claim
它有两个参数第一个是origin
It has two parameters. The first is origin
表示交易的发送方
It Indicates the sender of the transaction
第二个是我们存证的内容claim
The second is the content of our PoE claim
我们刚才提到它通常是一个哈希值
We just mentioned that it is usually a hash
我们这里用Max
We use Max here
U8来表示这样一个哈希的数据内容
u8 to represent the data content of such a Hash
返回一个DispatchResultWithPostInfo
It returns a DispatchResultWithPostInfo
这里我们还使用了
Here we also use
pallet::weight这样的宏
macros like pallet::weight
给我们的电话函数指定一个权重
to assign a weight to our callable function
这里我们给定了一个默认的
Here we have given a default
0这样的权重
0 such weight
之后的课程我们会介绍如何使用
Later in the course we will introduce how to use
benchmark to give weight a
benchmark来对权重进行
合适的定义
suitable definition
pallet call index宏
pallet call index macro
定义了可调函数在模块里的
defines the order of the callable function
顺序
in the module.
首先我们在create_claim可调函数里面
First of all, in the create_claim callable function
需要去校验我们的交易的发送方
we need to verify the sender of our transaction
我们的交易是一笔签名的交易
Our transaction is a signed transaction
同时我们要
At the same time we want
校验我们的
to check our
存证的存储项
storage item
proof里面不包含Bounded claim这样一个键
that the proof does not contain such a key as Bounded claim
也就是说我们这样的claim
That is to say, our claim
还没有存储到我们的
has not been saved to our
proof存证存储项里面
the proof storage item
如果存在我们返回一个错误
If it exists we return an error
ProofAlreadyExist
证明
to prove
这样的一个proof已经被别人去申请过
that such a proof has already been gotten by others
接着我们就可以使用proofs::::insert方法
Then we can use the proofs::::insert method
来插入我们的键值对
to insert our key-value pairs
这里我们的键是BoundedVector
Here our key is BoundedVector
也就是我们这里的Bounded claim
That is our Bounded claim here
以及它的值是一个2元素
and its value is a 2-element
Tuple是交易的发送方
Tuple that is the sender of the transaction
sender AccoutId表示我们的AccountId
sender AccoutId represents our AccountId
另外一个是我们的当前的区块数
The other is our current block number
我们使用系统模块提供的block_number
We use the block_number provided by the system module
这样的一个方法
such a method
成功的存储之后
After successful storage
我们就可以触发一个事件
we can trigger an event
ClaimCreated
表示我们的存证已经成功的被创建
It indicates that our PoE has been successfully created
紧接着我们返回一个OK
Then we return an OK
这样我们
So
创建存证的功能就已经完成了
the function of creating a PoE has been completed
我们可以看一下编译是不
We can see if the compilation is
是通过在编译之前
passed. Before compiling
我们需要把我们的存证模块
we need to add our certificate module
添加到我们的node template
to a space in Cargo.toml
所对应的Cargo.toml这样一个
that our node template
space里面
corresponds to.
我们这里要添加我们的pallet poe
We're going to add our pallet poe here
我们现在来编译一下
Let's compile it now
cargo build --release
来确认一下
to confirm
我们的代码是不是能够成功编译
does our code compile successfully
可以看到
We can see
我们现在就已经成功的编译了
it have now successfully compiled
接着我们来添加其他的可调用函数
Then let's add other callable functions
我们这里已经有了创建存证
We already have PoE creation
我们现在来添加
we will now add
删除存证这样的一个可调用函数
a callable function such as delete PoE
为了节省时间
To save time
我们就直接把代码一起放在这里
We'll just put the code together here
我们一起来看一下代码
Let's take a look at the code
删除存证
delete PoE
同样的我们给它一个pallet::weight(0)
Similarly we give it a pallet::weight(0)
来做一个默认的权重
to make a default weight
revoke_claim它有两个参数
revoke_claim which has two parameters
第一个是交易的发送方origin
The first is the sender origin of the transaction
另外一个是存证的哈希值Vector u8来表示
The other is the hash value Vector u8 of the PoE
我们首先也是校验
We also check
我们的交易是经过签名的
our transactions are signed
并且获得我们的交易的发送方sender
and get the sender of our transaction sender
接着我们要校验
Next we have to verify
我们的存证
that our PoE
已经存在在我们的proof存储项里面
has already existed in our proof storage item
不然的话我们就会报一个错误
Otherwise it will report an error
因为只有
because only
已经存储的存证才可以被吊销
stored PoE can be revoked
我们使用Proofs::get的方法
We use the Proofs::get method
传入我们的Bounded claim键来获取
to pass in our Bounded claim key to get
我们的proofs的值
the value of our proofs
如果不存在这样的一个
If there is no such a
键所对应的值的话
value corresponding to the key
我们就
we will then
证明我们的存储项里面并没有存储
prove that there is no claim stored
这样的一个claim
in our storage item.
我们返回一个ClaimNotExist的错误
We return a ClaimNotExist error
如果存储了这样的一个存证的话
If such PoE is stored
我们就返回对应的存储项的值
It returns the value of the corresponding storage item
它是两个元素中的Tuple第一
It is a Tuple of two elements. First
个元素是owner
element is owner
是我们的存证的拥有人。第二个
It represents the owner of the PoE. The second
元素是区块数
element is the number of blocks
包括number
including number
这里我们不关心所以用下划线
Here we don't care so use underscore
我们需要校验
we need to varify that
我们交易的发送方sender
sender of our transaction
是和我们的存证的拥有人owner
is the same with
是一致的
the owner of the PoE
不然的话我们就返回错误NotClaimOwner
Otherwise we return the error NotClaimOwner
接着我们就可以调用
Then we can call
Proofs存储项的remove方法来去删除
the remove method of the Proofs storage item to delete
对应key所
corresponding to the key
对应的存证
corresponding to the PoE
我们这样的key是Bounded claim
The key is Bounded claim
接着我们就可以触发一个事件
Then we can trigger an event
ClaimRevoked
才会OK我现在把我们的poe模块
It will be OK. I will now put our poe module
引入到我们的
into
runtime里面
the runtime
我们在runtime
In runtime
Cargo.toml里面
Cargo.toml
首先去引入pallet-poe模块
First import the pallet-poe module
因为它和pallet-template的很相似
Because it is very similar to pallet-template's
我们直接把
we directly
pallet-template复制一份并且修改必要的信息
copy the pallet-template and modify the necessary information
我们的模块是pallet-poe
Our module is pallet-poe
它所对应的路径是pallets目录下的poe
Its corresponding path is poe in the pallets directory
目录接着我们添加我们的编译标签
directory. Next we add our compile tag
我们在这里我们修改成pallet-poe
Here we modify it into pallet-poe
因为我们并没有
because we didn't
对pallet-poe进行runtime benchmark
use runtime benchmark for pallet-poe
所以我们不需要填
so we don't need to fill
runtime-benchmark标签
runtime-benchmark tag
try-runtime目前也不需要它是用来测试
try-runtime is not currently needed. It is used
链上的runtime升级的时候去
when the runtime on the chain is upgraded, go to
做一些链上数据的测试
to do some tests on the data on the chain
我们目前也不需要
We don't need it yet
添加完依赖之后
After adding dependencies
我们就可以在我们的runtime lib.rs
in our runtime lib.rs
源文件里面添加我们对应的
in the source file,  we can add our corresponding
poe模块实现
Poe module implementation
为了简单起见我们把template模块实现
For simplicity, we make a copy of the template module
复制一份
implementation
然后把它修改为我
and then modify it to
们的pallet-poe模块
pallet-poe module
跟这个接口里面有两个类型
There are two types in this interface
第一个是Event我们这里已经有了
The first one is Event we already have here
还有一个是MaxClaimLength
Another one is MaxClaimLength
这里我们使用Constu32是由我们的
Here we use Constu32
sp-runtime提供的这样一个帮助数据类型
such a helper data type provided by sp-runtime
Constu32表示
Constu32 represents that it
是一个满足get接口的u32类型
is a u32 type that satisfies the get interface
它的长度是我们这里给的是512
Its length is 512 as we give here
我们Bonded vector它的最大长度是512
Our Bonded vector has a maximum length of 512
接着我们把
Then we import
poe模块引入到我们的construct_runtime
the poe module into our construct_runtime
里面的Runtime
inside the Runtime
枚举里面
inside the enum
这里是
Here
PoeModule
pallet_poe
现在我们来编译
Now let's compile
可以看到现在已经编译成功了
You can see that the compilation is successful now
我们来在polkadot.js.apps的前端页面里面进行
Let's test it in the front-end page of
我们模块测试
polkadot.js.apps
我们首先运行我们的节点程序
We first run our node program
在
in
target/release/node-template这样一个二进制
a binary like target/release/node-template
可编译文件里面
such a the compilable file
我们运行
we run
它要使用--dev这样的一个标签
We need to use a label like --dev
来表示我们使用dev模式
to indicate that we use dev mode
可以看到现在节点已经启动起来了
You can see that the node is now started
并且有新的模块进行引入
and there are new modules to be imported
我们现在来进入我们的前端页面
Let's now go to our front-end page
polkadot.js.apps
我们使用我们的本地节点
We use our local node
Local Node 9944 switch
可以看到我们现在的区块正在生成
You can see that our current block is being generated
它的目标block time是6秒
Its target block time is 6 seconds
然后我们在我们的chain state
Then in our chain state
里面可以看我们的Poe模块
You can see our PoE module
然后它的Proofs给一个字节数
Then for its Proofs we give a byte count
以0X来开头 0X01
Start with 0X, 0X01
我们可以看一下这样的一个
We can take a look at that
key对应的值是不是存在
does the value corresponding to the key exist?
可以查询
We can query
可以看到它是None
You can see that it is None
表示我们key对应的值是不存在的
which indicates that the value corresponding to our key does not exist
我们现在来发送一笔交易
Let's send a transaction now
我们使用Alice
We use Alice
它有预制的余额
It has prefab balance
进入Poe模块create claim我们来
Enter the poeModule to create claim
对应key x等于1
Corresponding key x is equal to 1
我们现在来去创建一个claim
Let's create a claim now
那么它会存储到链上
Then it will be stored on the chain
待会我们去查询的话它应该就存在
It should exist if we check later
我们submit transaction
We submit transaction
等待交易确认
Waiting for transaction confirmation
可以看到现在交易已经确认了
You can see that the transaction has now been confirmed
再回到我们的chain state里面
Go back to our chain state
Poe模块
Poe module
Proofs
0x01
这样的key对应的值现在是否存在呢
Does the value corresponding to such a key exist now?
可以看到这时候它已经有了对应的值
You can see that it already has the corresponding value at this time
但是它的owner是这样一个地址
but its owner is such an address
也就是Alice的accountId
That is Alice's accountId
以及它的区块数是在
and its block number is
20的时候进行存储的
stored at 20
大家感兴趣的话
If you are interested
可以去测试一下revoke claim和
You can test revoke claim and
transfer claim这样的一个功能
a function such as transfer claim
我们今天课程的作业是
Our homework for today's class is
第一题是列出三个常用的宏
The first question is to list three commonly used macros
以及3个常用的存储数据结构
and 3 commonly used storage data structures
第2题是
Question 2 is
实现存证模块所需的基本功能
that implement the basic functions required by PoE
包括了创建存证和撤销存证
including creating PoE and revoking PoE
我们刚才在课程上已经一起写过
We have just written together in the course
第3题是
Question 3 is
为存证模块添加一个新的功能
to add a new function to the PoE
也就是转移存证
to transfer PoE
那这样的一个转移存证的可调用函数
Then such a callable function that transfers the PoE
有两个参数
has two parameters
那其实是3个参数
That's actually 3 parameters
第一个参数是交易的发送方
The first parameter is the sender of the transaction
那另外一个是我们存证内容的哈希值
The other one is the hash value of our certificate content
第三个参数是我们所需要
The third parameter is what we need
将存证所转移的一个目标地址
a target address to which the certificate will be transferred
也就是接收存证这样的一个账户地址
That is, an account address that receives PoE
今天课程的内容到这里就结束了
This is the end of today's lesson
谢谢大家
thank you all